<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Teares of ioy shed at the happy departure from Great Britaine, of the two paragons of the Christian world. Fredericke and Elizabeth, Prince, and Princesse Palatines of Rhine Duke and Dutches of Bauaria, &amp;c. By R.A.</title>
            <author>Allyne, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117998</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853207</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18576</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18576)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 906:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Teares of ioy shed at the happy departure from Great Britaine, of the two paragons of the Christian world. Fredericke and Elizabeth, Prince, and Princesse Palatines of Rhine Duke and Dutches of Bauaria, &amp;c. By R.A.</title>
                  <author>Allyne, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by N. Okes] for Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at his shop in the Popes-head-pallace, neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Robert Allyne.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Elizabeth, --  Queen, consort of Frederick I, King of Bohemia, 1596-1662 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18576:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18576:1"/>
            <p>TEARES OF IOY SHED At the happy departure from Great <hi>Britaine, of the two Paragons of</hi> the Chriſtian world.</p>
            <p>FREDERICKE and ELIZABETH, Prince, and Princeſſe Palatines of Rhine, Duke and Dutches of Bauaria, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> R. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iam redit &amp; virgo, redeunt Saturnia regna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in the Popes-head-pallace, neere the Royall Exchange. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedicatory_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18576:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18576:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE,</hi> SIR THOMAS ERS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KENE, LORD VICOVNT FENTON, Baron of Dirrilton, Captaine of his Maieſties <hi>Guards, Gentleman of his Highneſſe</hi> Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, and one of his Maieſties moſt Honorable Priuie Councell, &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY heart abhorres vngratefulneſſe, as hell,</l>
               <l>Yet how to cleere my ſelfe, I cannot tell.</l>
               <l>I do not plow the fertile plaines of <hi>Inde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe fruitfull gifts may match the giuers mind;</l>
               <l>I reape no harueſt, from rich <hi>Arabian</hi> fields;</l>
               <l>Nor drinke the golden ſtreames, that <hi>Ganges</hi> yeelds.</l>
               <l>My greateſt gift hath nothing to commend it,</l>
               <l>Except the giuers gratefull mind that ſend it,</l>
               <l>The leaſt in meanes, but not the laſt in loue,</l>
               <l>If equall power could poore goodwill approue.</l>
               <l>Which, if your honor, do but rightly weigh,</l>
               <l>A gratefull mind is more, then gold can buy;</l>
               <l>In ſigne whereof my ſimple <hi>Muſe</hi> affoords,</l>
               <l>A worthy ſubiect, drawne in worthleſſe words;</l>
               <l>A baſe-borne ſiſter to the ſacred <hi>Nine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which neuer yet did taſte <hi>Caſtalian wine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor ſund her ſelfe vpon <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> ſide;</l>
               <l>But liu'd obſcurely on the banke of <hi>Clide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A flood, beyond <hi>Permeſſis</hi> ſtreames in pleaſures,</l>
               <l>But vnacquainted with the <hi>Muſes</hi> meaſures.</l>
               <l>The field from whence theſe fruitles gifts do flow,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18576:3"/>
               <l>But new broke vp, in time may riper grow.</l>
               <l>Which if it do, if by exceſſe of toile,</l>
               <l>This barren field may turne a fertile ſoile;</l>
               <l>Vnto your Honor (though their vſe be ſmall)</l>
               <l>Ile conſecrate the field, the fruit, and all.</l>
               <l>Which once, I wiſh, may yeeld ſome greater worth,</l>
               <l>Or ſtill be barren, and bring nothing forth.</l>
               <l>Meane time, take this, not as the totall ſum,</l>
               <l>But as the intereſt of the reſt to come.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, Moſt obſequious ſeruant, Robert Allyne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18576:3"/>
            <head>Teares of loy.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SHall <hi>Brittaine</hi> then forgo her other eye,</l>
               <l>And lend her rareſt gemme, t'enrich the <hi>Rhine?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This ſpatious Ile, though all too ſtraight for <hi>three,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet large enough, wherein <hi>two</hi> lampes may ſhine.</l>
               <l>Why then? thogh heauens haue rob'd vs of the beſt,</l>
               <l>Shall diſtant roomes, diuide the two, that reſt?</l>
               <l>If nearneſſe of the one, make both obſcurer?</l>
               <l>Can diſtance adde more brightneſſe, then before?</l>
               <l>Is vertue, by it ſelfe ſequeſtred, purer?</l>
               <l>Then, when obumbrate by anothers glore.</l>
               <l>O ſure it is! Nor can this Northerne clime,</l>
               <l>Suſtaine two <hi>Sunnes</hi> together, at one time.</l>
               <l>This little world, within it ſelfe, confin'd,</l>
               <l>(Which <hi>Neptune</hi> from the greater world diuides)</l>
               <l>Whoſe lampes gaue light, beyond remoteſt <hi>Inde;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Muſt now diuide them, with the world beſides;</l>
               <l>And that, which late enioyd three lampes, alone,</l>
               <l>Now rob'd of <hi>two,</hi> muſt be content of <hi>one.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Go then <hi>(great Phebe)</hi> one halfe of our hope,</l>
               <l>And lend a new light, to an antient land;</l>
               <l>A light; that neither raging ſeas can ſtop,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Tagus</hi> quench, nor <hi>Tibers</hi> ſtreames withſtand.</l>
               <l>A light, a ſtarre, a fire, that ſhall conſume,</l>
               <l>And dim th'adulterate light of <hi>Spaniſh Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Feare not worſe fortune, in a forren part,</l>
               <l>Or loſſe of parents ſight, or lacke of friends,</l>
               <l>With one that caries more, then halfe thy heart,</l>
               <l>Whoſe breath, or death, vpon thy loue depends.</l>
               <l>And one, that glories more in being thine,</l>
               <l>Then being great commander of the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18576:4"/>
               <l>Behold a mighty land, a martiall ſoile,</l>
               <l>(Whom <hi>Caeſar</hi> had ſo much ado to dant,</l>
               <l>And to contain in duty; of whoſe ſpoile</l>
               <l>Victorious <hi>Rome</hi> had little cauſe to vant)</l>
               <l>To thee (great Dame) do greater homage yeeld,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Caeſar</hi> could enforce, in armed field.</l>
               <l>The ſoile it ſelfe, a fertile glebe of ground,</l>
               <l>Where golden <hi>Zephire</hi> pleaſant aire inſpires;</l>
               <l>Where graſſe, and graine, and <hi>Bacchus</hi> gifts abound,</l>
               <l>And all that nature needs, or vſe requires.</l>
               <l>Where chriſtal brooks, &amp; mettall-ſheering ſtrands,</l>
               <l>Infect their ſiluer ſtreames, with golden ſands.</l>
               <l>The fields, no leſſe delightfull there, then here;</l>
               <l>The plaines, irriguat with another <hi>Thames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A riuer, no leſſe delicate, and cleere,</l>
               <l>Deriuing, from the ſteepie <hi>Alpes,</hi> his ſtreames.</l>
               <l>Adorn'd with ſpatious parkes, in pleaſant rankes;</l>
               <l>And many <hi>Londons</hi> built vpon his bankes.</l>
               <l>A thouſand tributary torrents falles,</l>
               <l>And in his boſſome buries all their ſtate;</l>
               <l>Who like a maſſe, made vp of many ſmalles,</l>
               <l>Obſcures their memories, that made him great.</l>
               <l>By whoſe augmenting helpe, growne monſtrous huge</l>
               <l>He braues the <hi>Ocean,</hi> with a freſh deluge.</l>
               <l>Right ouer, and againſt, where ſtately <hi>Thames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Disburdens in the maine, his borrowed grouth,</l>
               <l>There changing both their natures, and their names,</l>
               <l>Each hath a proſpect, to the others mouth.</l>
               <l>That, if a way lay through the boundleſſe brine,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Engliſh Thames</hi> ſhold touch the <hi>Germain Rhine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſure it ſeemes, the gentle, fauouring waues,</l>
               <l>Haue yeelded paſſage, to theſe friendly floods,</l>
               <l>While winds, retiring in their trembling caues.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18576:4"/>
               <l>Did leaue calme ſeas, to welcome <hi>Neptunes</hi> broods,</l>
               <l>And father <hi>Ocean</hi> himſelfe conſented</l>
               <l>To haue his mighty ſonnes made more acquainted.</l>
               <l>Where, after ſome ſhort parly paſt betweene,</l>
               <l>They both did ſweare a ſolemne league of loue;</l>
               <l>A league, that ſhall not end, till <hi>Thames</hi> and <hi>Rhine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leaue off to run, or heauenly orbes to moue:</l>
               <l>And as they ſware, that ſo they meant to do,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Water-nymphes</hi> were witneſſes vnto.</l>
               <l>But leaſt ſucceeding ages might aledge</l>
               <l>Some friuole reaſons, to infringe their oath,</l>
               <l>Each did confirme the friendſhip with a pledge,</l>
               <l>Two rareſt Iewels, that adorn'd them both.</l>
               <l>And for more ſurety, 'twas agreed vpon,</l>
               <l>That both the Iewels were conioin'd in one.</l>
               <l>In whom, and in their ſacred ſeed, for euer,</l>
               <l>That louing league ſhall vndiſſolued ſtand,</l>
               <l>Which times, nor fates, nor death, cannot diſſeuer,</l>
               <l>Nor all the force of hels confederate band.</l>
               <l>Whoſe date (but new begun) ſhall ne're expire,</l>
               <l>Till firſt, this three-fold frame diſſolue in fire.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Tiber, Iber, Rodanus,</hi> and <hi>Seine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let <hi>Tygris, Tanais, Euphrates,</hi> and <hi>Nile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deſpiſe the heauen-bread-peace of <hi>Thames</hi> and <hi>Reine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In whoſe proud eyes theſe precious gems ſeeme vile.</l>
               <l>From theſe vnited flouds ſhall ſpring a flower,</l>
               <l>To ruine <hi>Tibers</hi> pride, and <hi>Ibers</hi> power.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Ganges</hi> glory in his golden ſands,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pactolus</hi> ſpread his ſtreames in ſtately rankes:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Indus</hi> lend his name to neigbouring lands,</l>
               <l>And throe deſpiſed pearles vpon his bankes.</l>
               <l>In your vnequal'd worths (O peereleſſe paire!)</l>
               <l>The <hi>Thames</hi> and <hi>Rhine</hi> are rich aboue compare.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18576:5"/>
               <l>Nor thou (O <hi>Forthe</hi>) muſt be exempt, in this,</l>
               <l>Whoſe merite equals either of the two,</l>
               <l>From thee proceeds the ground of both their bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Thou bred theſe Gemmes, that <hi>Thames</hi> enioyeth now.</l>
               <l>Theſe lights, theſe ſtars, that now adorne the earth,</l>
               <l>To thee, do owe their bloud, their breath, their birth.</l>
               <l>Ioyne with the two, and make the number three,</l>
               <l>(Three famous flouds, as earth cannot yeeld ſuch)</l>
               <l>That ſo in number, yee may equall be,</l>
               <l>To thoſe three Lampes, that grac'd you once ſo much.</l>
               <l>To whom (ſince one hath changed earth for heauen)</l>
               <l>One more ſucceeds, to make the number euen.</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Henry-Fredricke,</hi> lies in timeleſſe toome,</l>
               <l>Whoſe double name expreſt not halfe his worth;</l>
               <l>A <hi>Fredricke</hi> in his loſſe, ſupplies his roome,</l>
               <l>And bearing halfe his name, one halfe ſets forth</l>
               <l>Of him, whoſe all, is hardly match'd by two,</l>
               <l>And therefore is too much, for one, to do.</l>
               <l>Yet thou (braue youth) of all the ſonnes of men,</l>
               <l>Was onely worthy, to be one of three,</l>
               <l>Ranck'd in that roome, by him, who brook'd it then,</l>
               <l>And dying, did reſigne the ſame to thee,</l>
               <l>Who by a high inſtinct of heauenly grace,</l>
               <l>Left not the world, till thou aſſum'd his place.</l>
               <l>Go then, great Prince, and thou his other halfe,</l>
               <l>Grace of his youth, and glory of his age,</l>
               <l>Key of his ſecret thoughts, his ſecond ſelfe;</l>
               <l>Ioy in his care, and comfort in his rage;</l>
               <l>And each, in others debt, ſo deepe inuolued,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Gordius</hi> knot can ſooner be diſſolued.</l>
               <l>Go (royall pare) and let the <hi>Rhine</hi> augment,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Thames</hi> hath now ſo gloriouſly begun,</l>
               <l>And while, that lampe of life is yet vnſpent,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18576:5"/>
               <l>As <hi>Phaenix</hi> burnes herſelfe againſt the ſunne,</l>
               <l>That from her duſt may ſpring another one,</l>
               <l>To grace th' <hi>Arabian</hi> bounds when ſhe is gone:</l>
               <l>So now, raiſe vp a world of royall ſeed,</l>
               <l>That may adorne the earth when ye are dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To <hi>FREDERICKE,</hi> Prince Palatine of <hi>RHINE,</hi> Duke of <hi>BAVARIA, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>GReat off-ſpring of a high Imperiall Race,</l>
               <l>And now allyed with a Royall kinde,</l>
               <l>whoſe worth exceeds thy years, whoſe glorious place</l>
               <l>Is more then matched, by a generous minde.</l>
               <l>Whoſe outward grace, and inward gifts are ſuch,</l>
               <l>As higheſt veines cannot expreſſe too much.</l>
               <l>Yet neither doth thy race, nor place, nor worth,</l>
               <l>Nor theſe rare parts of body, and of minde,</l>
               <l>Nor all thy merits, halfe ſo much ſet forth</l>
               <l>Thy happineſſe, as being now combin'd</l>
               <l>In loue, and life, with one, whoſe vertues ſhall</l>
               <l>Adde new renowne, to race, and place, and all.</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Caeſar</hi>-maker, thou whoſe powerfull vote,</l>
               <l>Can raiſe a ſubiect to the Imperiall hight;</l>
               <l>Thou canſt make Emperours, and haſt thou not</l>
               <l>In creating an Empreſſe equall might?</l>
               <l>Expreſſe it then vpon thy better halfe,</l>
               <l>And in aduancing her, raiſe vp thy ſelfe.</l>
               <l>That both together gracing <hi>Caeſars</hi> chaire,</l>
               <l>Thy ſonne may bee <hi>Arch-ſewer</hi> to his ſire.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18576:6"/>
            <head>TO <hi>EIZABETH</hi> Princeſse <hi>PALATINE</hi> of <hi>RHINE,</hi> Dutches of <hi>BAVARIA.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>MIrrour of vertue, Beauties blazing ſtarre,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe worth amazes earths remoteſt ends,</l>
               <l>A peece, which nature to adorne ſo farre,</l>
               <l>In skorne of Art, her vtmoſt skill extends.</l>
               <l>VVhere <hi>Pallas, Venus, Iuno's</hi> giftes are ſuch,</l>
               <l>That skarſe they haue reſeru'd themſelues ſo much.</l>
               <l>And muſt thou th<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <hi>(great dame)</hi> withdraw theſe beams,</l>
               <l>And darke this Ile, fr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o whence thou draws thy ſtampe,</l>
               <l>Is all the circuite, betwixt <hi>Tay</hi> and <hi>Thames,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Too ſtraite a limite, for ſo great a Lampe?</l>
               <l>That ſo to giue thy glory greater vent,</l>
               <l>Thou muſt poſſeſſe the ſpacious continent.</l>
               <l>Yet though thy bodie be remou'd to <hi>Rhine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy name ſhall ſtill thy natiue Ile adorne,</l>
               <l>Thy glory in the furtheſt North ſhall ſhine;</l>
               <l>And (as the Sunne, through vapors ſeene, at Morne,</l>
               <l>Appeares a larger body, to the eye,</l>
               <l>Then when he mountes the high Meridian skie)</l>
               <l>Thy beames ſhall from beyond the <hi>Belgicke</hi> ſhore,</l>
               <l>Shine ſtill as bright, and brighter then before.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Collatio.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat wonder was't, that Mortalleies did weepe,</l>
               <l>VVhen heauens th<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſelues could not abſtain fr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o tears?</l>
               <l>What courſe in mourning, could the looſers keepe,</l>
               <l>When thoſe, that gain'd ſo much, ſo ſad appeares</l>
               <l>But when times alter'd, with a milder turne,</l>
               <l>Then heauens, &amp; earth did both leaue off to mourn.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18576:6"/>
               <l>What wonder was't, that mortal breaſts did grone,</l>
               <l>When winds, &amp; waues, could not containe their griefe?</l>
               <l>Or what could ſtil the cheifeſt mourners mone,</l>
               <l>When ſympathyzing things found no reliefe?</l>
               <l>Till wedding ioyes, did weeping woes exile,</l>
               <l>Then ſea, and aire, did both beginne to ſmile.</l>
               <l>What wonder is't that mortals leaue their mones,</l>
               <l>When heauen themſelues haue chang'd their mourning cheere?</l>
               <l>What wonder is't, that earth forgets her grones,</l>
               <l>VVhen ſea, and aire, are growne ſo calme and cleere?</l>
               <l>O happy change! that heauens and earth doth turne,</l>
               <l>And ſeas, and aire, to mirth, that late did mourne.</l>
               <l>Heauens, at our ſorrowes, ſeem'd not halfe ſo ſad,</l>
               <l>As now they ioy, to ſee ſuch ioy on earth,</l>
               <l>Nor windes, were at our mourning halfe ſo mad,</l>
               <l>As now th'are pleas'd, and partners in our mirth;</l>
               <l>Nor at our griefe, the ſeas grieu'd halfe ſo much,</l>
               <l>As now made calme, they ioy, that our ioye's ſuch.</l>
               <l>This lower element, is but the center,</l>
               <l>To which, the other's dregs, do downe-ward moue,</l>
               <l>That in the ſame, nor griefe, nor ioy can enter,</l>
               <l>But what the other three effect aboue,</l>
               <l>And mortall things that on the baſe earth breed,</l>
               <l>Moue by ſuperiour powers, as by their head.</l>
               <l>But thou that ſwayes this lands Imperiall Mace,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſpirit doth inſpire, and moue this Ile;</l>
               <l>And yee, his royall Queene, and Princely race,</l>
               <l>Though earth confine your perſons for a while,</l>
               <l>Yet more then earthly is your ſacred power,</l>
               <l>Which beares a kinde of rule or'e all the foure,</l>
               <l>For as yee ſeeme too grieue or ioy on earth,</l>
               <l>Fire, aire, and ſeas, incline to griefe, or mirth.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
